<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A negative voyce: or, A check for your check: being a message (by a black-rod) of non-concurrence, for the ballancing-house, or co-ordinate senate: fairly discussing the security it can give, to the good old cause.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89891</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863111</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115293</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248550337</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1010_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203000</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863111</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863111e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 150:E1010[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A negative voyce: or, A check for your check: being a message (by a black-rod) of non-concurrence, for the ballancing-house, or co-ordinate senate: fairly discussing the security it can give, to the good old cause.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Legislative bodies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115293:1"/>
            <p>A Negative Voyce: OR, A Check for your Check: <hi>BEING</hi> A Message (by a Black-Rod) of Non-concurrence, for the Ballancing-House, or Co-ordinate <hi>SENATE:</hi> Fairly Discussing the Security it can give, To the Good Old Cause.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. XXVII. 5, 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Open Rebuke is better then Secret Love.</p>
               <p>Faithful are the Wounds of a Friend; but the Kisses of an Enemy are Deceitful.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115293:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115293:2"/>
            <head>A Negative Voice: <hi>OR, A Check for your Check:</hi> Being a Message (by a Black-Rod) of Non-concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, for the Ballancing-House, or Co-ordinate <hi>SENATE:</hi> Fairly discussing the security it can give to the <hi>Good old Cause.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter so unlikely and prodigious an apperance of God for the recovery of our Freedome, no doubt it must needs now be our wisdome, to play the Men; and no more to tempt God to work wonders for us, but to secure the honest Interest of such as have been the grand Assertors of our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by such wayes and means, as may become rational, honest, and Christian men: But it may so fall out, while we profess our selves Wise, we may become Fools; and remembring how we have been hunted from the Hills to the Mountains, &amp; from thence to the tops of the Trees; we may now go about to build a Tower above the reach of danger; such a Fabrick is in rearing (in the opinion of some) under the title of <hi>A Co ordinate Senate,</hi> that will certainly secure the Interest of the Common-wealth, (and it may be one would hardly think otherwise, without a more narrow disquisition, then every one will be at the pains of:) to the which, if God suffer the Top-stone to be laid, and do not come down, and confound our Language, and cause the work to cease, I must believe God will yet again tread down our strength, and shew us that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115293:3"/>we are but Men: We will therefore put our selves in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, though we once knew this, how we have put confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in lies, and <hi>made Lies our Refuge,</hi> (I mean such things as have deceived us) when yet it is like we meant every jot as honestly, and were as sollicitous as now to secure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of such, as had contended against Tyranny: I would not cause their wound to bleed afresh, who have very inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously prevented others, from renewing their complaints against them, by complaining of themselves, lately; but let us mind the Successes we have had, and by them conclude the Good Speed we are like to have in this new Device: was it not once thought, (if it were not, we are grievously bely'd) and essayed too, that the King should be restored, and some of the honest party, sit down at his right hand, and at his left in his Kingdom, and that would be good Security? and are we not otherwise perswaded since, to trust neither King, nor House of Peers: Was it not once thought this Parliament were men whom God would not honour in his work, and therefore they were disturbed, and are we of that opinion still? Did we not pick and choose such as were approved out of all Counties, for honesty and godliness, and made no doubt then but all would succeed to our hearts content, and were we at all the wiser?</p>
            <p>Afterwards, as if in the <hi>Multitude of Counsellors there had been</hi> no <hi>safety;</hi> and as if all honesty, and our Good Old Cause had had been combined in a single Person, we must have a <hi>Protector;</hi> in whose hands no question many honest hearts would have ventured their All: Of so great esteem was he for his godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; who, though <hi>out of weaknesse was made strong, had waxed valiant in fight, and turned to flight whole Armies of Allens</hi> and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; yet was not the matter much amended: His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of Government was soon out of tune; and the <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition and Advice,</hi> as a more hopefull security, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited for the Standard of our Government, and this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Nay a great while: yet now our conviction is risen higher, (our wit being bought dear enough) we must learn our Lesson back again; and that very parliament, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one thought it his vertue to cast Dirt upon, is now by a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115293:3"/>stupendious hand of providence, (beyond President) vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from the reproach of tongues, and made way for, as the only repairers of our breaches, and estorers of paths for us to dwell in: So that for these six years past we have laboured in the very fire, and though we may seem to be putting on apace, towards the good land of Peace and Rest; yet so it may be, (if we follow this way of our own heart,) few of us are like to enter in; but may make up more then forty years wandring in a Wildernesse; and that <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joshua</hi> may not now be, who shall live to enter in with the good people of these Nations, into rest from their enemies round about: Nor our Childrens Children see the day, that many now look for; when they shall reap the benefit of our bloud, and treasure: We should then by former harms learn to beware, and having cleerly discovered our selves not at all to be guided by an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Spirit; we should be the more wary of the Brats of our own Brains, and as watchful over the Fancies of others, and examine things throughly, before we produce them as neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary expedients for the healing of the <hi>Daughter of our people;</hi> and I am apt to believe, when this <hi>Co-ordinate Senate</hi> shall be sifted to the bottome (which I dare not pretend to do, only to meet with some things, that lye not very remote from a common understanding) that many who now cry up, this <hi>Diana,</hi> wil bite their fingers &amp; repent of their hast. Now because I would save from making <hi>new work for repentance</hi> (if it be not too late) I shall say enough, though not half what might be said, to perswade them to consider awhile, before they spur on any further, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the perching of such a <hi>Power,</hi> as I doubt me, they would be glad in a short time to unroost, if they knew how.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Senate of select persons to be chosen, Co-ordinate in Power with the</hi> Parliament, <hi>is petitioned for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If by the Name, we may guess at the Nature of the thing, it is as like the other <hi>House,</hi> as an <hi>Ape</hi> is like a <hi>Monkey;</hi> but because it is new, both Name, and thing, let us enquire, how it may probably be Midwived into the World, and observe how well it is calculated for the <hi>Meridian</hi> of our Liberty, and Security, &amp; so perhaps we may perceive some benigne Aspects, that may portend some more favourable Events, then yet it hath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115293:4"/>promised me, under the most charitable considerations, my reason can suggest: the power to be deposited into the hands of the Senate, must be this at least, That without them, nothing may be made perfect: they must strike the dead stroak: <hi>A Negative Voyce</hi> they shall have over the Parliament, that is the plain English of it: So that the good people of the Land shall send up their Representers in Parliament, to make what Lawes for them, please the Senate: that such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, is for the declared-for Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> they that now Petition for it, have over and over confuted: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the grand stickling will be that it is for our security, (having learned more to minde that, then our integrity) and it will be imagined, if it be not already concluded; that nothing lesse then such a select Number of persons, to concurre in all transactions of State; can be sufficient security, against the violent irruptions of those Monarchical and Anarchical Spirits, who on the one hand, and on the other, are so many and so ready, (wanting only opportunity) to spoil us of all our sore travel we have had under the Sun; for the setling these Nations upon the foundations of Righteousness and Freedome: Such a select number of persons then must be chosen for our security, chosen (no doubt) by this Parliament, and by them vested (if they can be perswaded to it, but I wish better,) with such a power, as may for ever hereafter, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Representatives of no more signification then Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: But I trow the next Parliament may take the like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to pluck them down, as these to set them up, and then our security is as good as spoiled: for I cannot learn how this Parliament should have more power then the next: but if this must be like the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> and they must not here touch our Coppy-hold; but this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment must give away that which is none of their own, (for such I account the powers of succeeding Parliaments) yet (with most reason) so much power shall be left to the next Parliaments, that they may put in new Members, upon the death, or misdemeanors of the former; if not so, yet they may have leave left them to nominate persons, (being but a small courtesie) and the Senate to concurre; which if the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115293:4"/>Parliament will not nominate to the good liking of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, (for it is more then a Co-rodinate Power, that the Senate should take into their number who they please, without the concurrence of the Parliament) I know in a few years, (if they cannot mould a Parliament to their Faction) what will become of the Senate, and security both; Well, this is but nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; no question this will be easily foreseen, and prevented: Such a Senate shall be nominated, and so constituted, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently (like a young Cuckoe) shall be too hard for the Dam; after Parliaments shall do nothing without them; if any Member of the Senate die, or be displaced, themselves shall call in whom they please to supply their vacancy (for thus the security must be compleated, if it be compleat) and after this manner, Senators shall beget Senators, to the end of the Chapter; by a strange kinde of Coition, men with men doing those things that are unreasonable; wherein they will have the good luck of it, to be abundantly more happy then the Parliament; who, good men, though they have the title of <hi>The Supream Authority of the Nation,</hi> have not yet the power to chuse one single Member into their House: The matter then thus stated to our good liking: A S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nate consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, to confirm, or make void all Deliberations of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and they set above an account to any but God, and themselves; (being not fit they should be tryed, by any but their Peers) for if they should I would not be in their Coats, for all the Cloaths on their backs) having also the sole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Senators to fill up their numbers; and all this confirmed by this present Parliament, with all Powers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to their Grandeur, not to be reversed without highest Treason; yet it is something a Question to me Whether this would be standing security; and good Publick Faith to rest upon: I would scarce advise the Army to lay down their Weapons, and hazard their Stakes upon this Lottery; or, though I should, I doubt their faith would fail them; and so would mine: The reasons of my unbelief are:</p>
            <p>First, Because I have observed Plots, every whit as well laid, with as honest pretensions, not at all to succeed, to the expectations of the well-meaning Promoters: what may be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115293:5"/>thought of the little Convention at <hi>Westminster,</hi> in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament House, (immediately after the disturbing of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) which more then a few expected Great matters from, for the good of the Nation; (a strange implicit Faith to me) who were furnished with a Negative and Affirmative Voice too (saving alwayes the power of the Sword) who were as select, and chosen a number, as men could cull, and seek out of the Nation; and yet these did great matters to be talked of, but not one jot to the purpose; and yet we will believe, most of the now Army Designed for a Senate, did then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily think the nail was knockt on the head; and clenched fast enough to secure the honest Party: after that we never thought all our own, till we had patched up another, or the Other House: (who were never Christened a House of Lords, and therefore no more Anticstristian then a Senate) And now no doubt the Master-builders thought all Cock-sure, for, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controversie it was not resolved with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut mature delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: And yet all these Bonds are broken, and these new Cords snapt in sunder like a threed: We shall see whether these green Withs will binde us to afflict us; and whether when these <hi>Philistines</hi> are upon us, we shall not rouse up our selves, and shake us as at other times.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Methinks i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sorts not well with our renewed Declarations, Protestations, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etensions; and our Troth plighted to God and Men: And therein I think did lie the weaknesse of former Buildings: For although men may be surprized to betray themselves, by a fair colour put upon a soul face; yet if they retain a common sense, when they shall finde time, and cause of recoll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction, (and it is more then pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible they may have enough) they may chance not to forget former promises, but remember from whence they are fallen; and repent; beway I their back slidings and Apostasy, (with shame enough) and ruine the work of their own hands; and so our destruction shall be of our selves, of which we are not now without example: Were it not better, if we erre through in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dvertency not to utter our mindes, presently, not to be rash with our lips, if we are abused by Juglers, not to be so true proofs, and manifest demonstrationsof <hi>Solomons</hi> Text
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115293:5"/>— <hi>The simple believeth every word:</hi> but with serious, and honest consideration, laying aside the Weights of Self-love, and Self-will (sins that do easily beset us) <hi>run with patience the race that is set before us:</hi> shewing our Wisdome, as well as our Faith, in not making over-much hast, and so save our selves the labour and shame of a Reprisall and Repentance: to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare against a <hi>House of Lords,</hi> or the Other <hi>House</hi> (call it what you will) as Arbitrary and Tyrannicall; and to petition for a <hi>Senate,</hi> every manner of way as injurious, and that must have as much power to the full: This <hi>Vizard</hi> must needs fall off, being just as good fore-cast, as to depose <hi>Kingship,</hi> and set up a <hi>Protector;</hi> and they that found out the Knavery of the one, will in all likelyhood, in some time, find out the Jest of the other; which when they do (if we be not already Pistol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof) we may quickly go look out new Security for our <hi>Good old Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Because I observe a very honest Spirit, posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the minds of many, who would venture hard, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, and righteous things might take place amongst us, who have been so often cheated, and mis-led, that they begin now, like prudent men, to look well to their way: and I dare say, the Designs for a <hi>Senate,</hi> would be very unwilling to submit the honesty of it, to the Enquiry, and Judgment of Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall men; however should such a power be constituted by this <hi>Parliament</hi> (as such whom they had chosen out of the World) yet could not this Lyon be thought so tame, as that his Paws should need no paring; nor I think give much satisfaction to any to come under his Clutches, for it is now well received, that it matters not so much whom we trust, as the Power they are betrusted with; it being good to keep the Staff in the right hand: And I think honest Principles, (there are so many Disputes about Painciples) are more hardly discoverable, then honest men (I speak not this altogether of men in Rule) having therefore been so long in the Quest of honest Principles, and having been hitherto at a loss, and yet well nigh turned every stone; 'tis a venture but some good Friends or other of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> may at length prick them out for us; and if we shall have so good
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115293:6"/>chance as to hit upon them, as there are generally good hopes we may shortly (though alwayes the Game doth not go with the greatest Cry) I dare say, if we have Power in our hands to do it, we shall follow them with shoutings, and bear them up (at the expence of all) above the reach of Envy, in despight of Lordly and slavish Spirits; and hunt those Foxes to their Holes, if we do not send in fire after them (how well soever the Geese they run away with at their backs, or Backs may scape) who have carried Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands in their Tayls, and burnt up, not our Corn only, but our Liberties, Honours, and Reputations in the world. I doubt me, the vengeance of all their Inquities will find them out, and follow them at their Heels, and be poured out abundantly upon their Heads, by the incensed, and abused People; judge all the World, if this be not rather in view, then a Settlement, and then for all their Co-ordinate <hi>Senate,</hi> or their Penitentiall acknowledgments of former Apostasies, they will be like to be put hard to it, to use their Wits, to find new Security for their <hi>Good old Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is in Diametricall opposition, unto Cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Uniting; it cannot but occasion Feuds, and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings between the <hi>Senate,</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> if we shall yet have any more <hi>Parliaments</hi> (and this is like to be good Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) it must needs thereby occasion diffences between all sorts of men in the Nation, who will be fiding, according to their severall Interests and Opinions: It is hardly imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, how the Peoples <hi>Representatives</hi> will be content, that their Sheaves shall fall down, and do Obeysance to their younger Brothers Sheaf; they must needs see the <hi>Good old Cause</hi> was blind, and cannot live long after it, since these men have got the Blessing; and will certainly look upon them, as very wilely men, having this second time deceived them: they cannot but take notice, by what over-ruling Power, the Armes (of this <hi>Good old Cause</hi>) were crossed, to lay its right hand upon this <hi>Youth,</hi> against the good liking of every honest <hi>Joseph</hi> in the Land; Here must needs now be old heaving, and lifting at one another (we see how well two <hi>Parliaments</hi> already have fadged with the other House,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115293:6"/>which was pretty cunningly fitted for a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> a <hi>Senate</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never like to sute one half quarter so well with a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi>) and this not like to end, but in supplanting the one, or the other: If this <hi>Storm</hi> should overwhelm the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Goodnight for ever, might the good People of this Land say, to all their Liberties, and Immunities, which is to be hoped we should bustle hard for, before we would part with; if it should light upon the <hi>Senate,</hi> and their Co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Power should faile of being co-equall force, and they necessitated to give away (which I am abundantly more willing to hope for) then <hi>Hic labor, Hoc opus,</hi> our Security is <hi>Doct</hi> in the Entail; so that in all appearance, here will be fine Nosing, and Bearding, Garbling, Purging, Dissolving, and so <hi>Ad infinitum;</hi> and then, Whether this Kingdome divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it self (though it were <hi>Satans</hi> for its Devices) would stand long, and not be brought to a Desolation, is a just Case.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It must needs be a perpetuating of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> which must needs occasion Discontents, and Disturbances, unto the honestest Party of the Army themselves, and all sorts of men, when they shall be out of doubt, that it is even so; and that this cannot end, but in breaking them to pieces; I think I may foretell without the Spirit, or Gift of Prophesie: the Army having again, and again, declared against Perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in Power (not excepting these very men) and the whole Nation greedily eying them; whether they did indeed design (what the Army formerly cast in their Dish) to continue themselves to the Worlds end; who if they should throw this Knick-knack out of doors, as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that neither we, nor our Children shall be able to bear, will make them to be found Lyars, who never Prophesied Good, but Evill of them, and shall be had in admiration of this, and after Ages; for the most truly deserving Patriots, and self-denying <hi>Parliament,</hi> ever any Age produced (a sore temptation to resist) and Generations unborn, <hi>shall rise up and call them blessed:</hi> But if it go on roundly, then to be sure this Parliament must nominate and constitute this Power; and who will doubt but (according to the Modell of the Councel
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115293:7"/>of State) at least two parts, of three must be of their own number, and those only left to suffer a Dissolution, who may be well enough spared; and it may be for us it were better they were in, then out; have we not brought our Hoggs then to a fair Market, and by this time, whether a Party will be found to bear up this Fabrick, that will be so blinded with Rewards, as not to see this <hi>Co-ordinate Senate,</hi> and this everlasting <hi>Parliament,</hi> to be one, and the same thing (saving only the disturbing, or putting a Period to the Remnant, (every jot as honest as the rest) and the taking in some others (every whit as bad as the best) whether this then be like to hold water, and prove a sufficient Cloak for the <hi>Good old Cause;</hi> or rather, such a Spirit be not in a fair way to get up; as may not be layd but in the ruine of them, or us, or both (having had sufficient provocation) is rather to be expected, then to be had in doubt.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, 'Tis a perfect <hi>Treppan,</hi> an under-ground Plot, and will cheat us of our <hi>Good old Cause,</hi> rather then secure it; if this were not the Design of it, yet is it as handsomly fitted for such Designes, as ones heart could desire: This <hi>Senate</hi> is pretended to Hedge us in on every side, to hedge up our way with Thorns, if so be we should but look toward <hi>Monarchy:</hi> (believe it who will) but in the mean time is a prick in our Eyes, and a Goad in our sides; and will teach us the way of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as <hi>Gideon</hi> taught the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> with Thorns and Bryars: to do things honest and just in the sight of men, would tend towards a settlement; and it may be too, discover the Wedge and <hi>Babylonish</hi> Garment: therefore Baits must be layd for maintaining Jealousies, under pretence of Christian Prudence (by which I have found many hooked in of late (I believe as honest well-meaning men, as any are in the world) to say as they say, there must be a Check up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Parliament,</hi> reasons of <hi>State</hi> require it, if we should trust the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they will be generally Malignant, and would use us but coursly, therefore let us have a <hi>Senate</hi> by all means: away with such a Fellow, it is not fit he should live, that is not for self-preservation; and many a <hi>Barnabas</hi> is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with this Dissimulation) Grievances must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115293:7"/>as much Oppression, yea, if possible the same Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions under a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as under <hi>Monarchy</hi> (and this dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly to supplant us) the Waters must be troubled, or else that will not come to Net they are fishing for; only for a spetious pretence, to amuse such as can see no farther into a Milstone then other men; there shall be a new Name to an old thing, (grown it may be so much more then formerly, a Match for us, by its Experiences and Refinings) yea, and it may be too, some plausible things, generally wished for, may be done to stop our Mouthes: And yet notwithstanding these Fig-leaves must drop off, and the nakedness and shame appear, and we shall be able without Spectacles, to know a Pig from a Dog, and to call a Spade, a Spade, for all the Shuttle: and shall not stick to say, This <hi>Senate</hi> (call it what you will) is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed worse then the old <hi>House of Lords,</hi> or the late <hi>Other House,</hi> and prayes <hi>Rex</hi> over the Parliament, we can have few honest things done for the good of the Nation: and now out, and alass, all the Fat is in the Fire, we are never the better for our <hi>Common-wealth</hi> (it works now) <hi>Monarchy</hi> was as good every jot; we shall never have quiet, nor enjoy our Liberties, till we are gone the Round, and the old Spoke gets uppermost (then have at all) let us back again into <hi>Aegypt; Who is this Moses?</hi> And, <hi>who is this Aaron?</hi> What is this <hi>Good old Cause</hi> to us? it is a meer Fetch, a meer Trick, it will never be better with us then it was, every Party Gulls us of our Liberties; we had as good be Slaves to them that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver promised us better, as to these Pretenders, we will be cheated no longer by them: What shall we do now? Can any better way be found out, to still the noyse of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Tumults of the People (for the Plot is as right, to set the Parliament, Senate, and Army together by the Eares, as if it had been done for the purpose; that a Kite may end the Quarrell) now then let us have a King, after the manner of other Nations round about us; for a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> will please the People no longer; and then on a main for an Humble Petition and Advice, or something of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and daily Entreaties of all the good People of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if possible to keep the <hi>Stuarts</hi> out while they are out)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115293:8"/>to force some good man to snatch away the Government (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his will) out of the hands of our New thing, Nothing; New thing, Old thing, Kingdome, Common-wealth; and this too, no question, good Christian Prudence, in case of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, as we have been put to many Necessities of late; or if yet we should retain so much sense of Honour, and Honesty, (as without breach of Charity, may be a little questioned, having given notable Proofs of our Constancy formerly) and conclude the World would cry shame on us, if we should (Faces about) build again the thing we had destroyed, or suffer any single person to usurp the Government: &amp; so put a stop to this Carier: yet quickly some other expedient might be found out and produced (every jot as wise as Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship) that may gratifie the gaping Ambition of some, who might be at the Disciples question, <hi>Which of them should be the greatest;</hi> for it is possible no single States-man, hath so much got the start of some others, as to be able to swallow this Morsell alone; however the nimblest of them, that best can, may get into the Saddles together, and agree well enough (though it may be, amongst themselves, like Cats and Dogs) to Lord it over us: and then he might be thought worthy of a Cap, and a Feather, and to be no small Officer of State: who would whet his Tongue, and his Pen to shoot the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of bitter words, and declaim against all former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and bend his Forces might, and main, to advance your <hi>Triumviri,</hi> or a <hi>Decem-viri,</hi> rather then fail; or exhibit some Scripture Government, some Seventy Elders of the People; and then hap and beluckey, come what can come (though worse then stark nought) if we can keep out the <hi>Stuarts;</hi> Ay, and it may be too, if that be the worst on't) we shall draw Stakes: If we should lick up our Vomit for such a Government, as cannot be without an <hi>House of Lords,</hi> or the <hi>Other House,</hi> here is a <hi>Senate</hi> to your Tooth, out of which you may have the Mistresse, and her Hand-maids, if they can agree about it, or a Lot decide the matter; here is choyce of all sorts, you may have a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>House of Lords,</hi> an <hi>Imperatour, Protector,</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> and <hi>Another-House;</hi> or what you please:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115293:8"/>according to the chance of the day: for no question here shall be packt together, such as lye next in the way of preferment; that if there do not fall out a good rub, must needs be knockt up to the Jack Head, and carry it away with them: such as would look as big as Bull-bief at— <hi>If it please your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, May it please your most serene Highnesse:</hi> That it is like, they thought the worse of Monarchy, that they were not Monarchs themselves: Here you may have Three, or Ten, what Fits the turn; of the best Head-pieces, Honestest men, and fittest to Rule that can be found in <hi>England,</hi> and leave a Senate still, if need so require, (having power to recruit the number at discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) for, it may be, as long as Parliaments shall be thought fit to be continued, it will not be thought amisse to keep up a <hi>Ballancing House;</hi> What would you have more? Must it be Seventy <hi>Elders</hi> of the People? No question, this must be the last of the Play; when they Can neither Will nor Chuse; (it not being like to be the design, of the most Leading Men) but though this prevail, here is a Senate can do the work: who, should their name by this time prove an <hi>Oppression,</hi> can forgoe their <hi>Christendome,</hi> and renew their Baptisme; and then <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Pocus Prester Senate</hi> be gone, Come forth <hi>Seventy Elders;</hi> — Here you have it Sirs, whole for your purpose; here will need no chopping, nor changing; Every one shall put in to share a <hi>Monarchy:</hi> (no question, the most equal distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can be) And now farewell Parliament: It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard that such a Government needed a Parliament. What, a Scripture Government, and need a Parliament? Fie, upon it: No, <hi>the Lord Reigns, let our Islands be glad thereof; the Saints Rule, who have made warre with the Beast, and overcome; And who can be more fit to sit down every Man upon his Throne, judging the Tribes of</hi> England; And by this time, I hope, the <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> is safe enough. Speak now, is not here rare Forecast? At the long run you will finde we are entangled like a Bull in a Net, and one way or other our Lords will be our Masters; and then farewell for ever to that Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that is now in our hands, to Vindicate the Liberties and Just Priviledges of our Native Countrey, out of the Clutches of those <hi>Sycophants;</hi> those <hi>Apes</hi> that would fain be thought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115293:9"/>the <hi>Fathers</hi> of our <hi>Liberties,</hi> that Hugge us to death with their Simulation, with their Dissimulation: He that doth not now foresee this, is as blinde as <hi>Bayard:</hi> And should we Bray him in a Morter, it would be all A-case. However, I think I have found the Security so Litigious, that to make an Estate upon this Good Old Cause, I hold no man in his right Wits, would give half Seven years Purchase for a Life upon it: Wherein I have said not so much as I could, (having only thought fit to meet with such things, as offered themselves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the pretended Security) touching the unconscionable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, unreasonablenesse and unjustnesse of this <hi>Co-ordinate Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate;</hi> knowing it not much worth my labour; believing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one would give me <hi>Jobs</hi> answer, <hi>What you know, we know also, who knoweth not such things as these?</hi> For I suppose, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors; yea the very Promoters and Promulgers of this strange New-fangled, New-fashion'd thing, would quit the Vindication of it, under this notion, if they could be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of a better Security, that might sort with their Interests and Concernments; Which it may be, are not all so very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, as to endure the Fiery Furnace of a <hi>Parliaments</hi> Supreme Authority, and to <hi>come forth, having no smell of the Fire upon their Garments:</hi> And therefore, they will <hi>set up, and fall down, and worship this Golden Image of their own hands;</hi> and serve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to cast in all others into this Oven, <hi>heated one seven times hotter then the other,</hi> for all such as will not Bow down to this Head of Brasse, and Hands of Iron. Well, but had I not as good have spoken to the Poast all this while? Or, shall I not bring an Old House about my Ears? Will not many be vilely vex'd, and ask, <hi>What ails this Doughty Champion, this Stripling not a span long? We know the pride and naughtinesse of thy heart; thou art come down to see the Battell, to espie our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and see us fall in the Fight.</hi> It is no hard matter to pick Holes in ones Coat; easier by much to <hi>finde</hi> Faults, then to <hi>mend</hi> them: We may finde one thing or other amisse in every Government; there is nothing <hi>perfect</hi> under Heaven. Pish, these are but the Whimsies of a Sick Brain, of a sorry Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly Pate; such as are alwayes <hi>speaking evil of Dignities, and fo those things they know not;</hi> Surely we mean honestly now, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115293:9"/>never, but can never please all: We wonder what you would have, if you could speak: Better a Bad Government (and this is not so bad, as it is made) then none at all: — Wherein it is like, I should jump in your judgement, if were reduced to such extreams; But it is clear, we are not yet in such distress: I am sure we have, or at least (within this few Weeks) we had got the Weather gage; and might have done as Honest things, as ever were promised: But, if we tack about, and stand for the Old Course, I must write <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> upon our Parliaments, upon the Honest Men in the Army, (if there be any such, as I believe there are some:) upon our Lawes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and our <hi>All;</hi> they are upon departing, unlesse he that made the Sun go back so many Degrees upon the Dial, cause their Sun to goe down at Noon, who pretend what they intend not. But all this while you have not told us of Better Security, for such as have made themselves the Mark of Envy, by interposing for the Good People of these Nations: 'Tis very true; neither do I know, whether you would like it ever the better, if I should: And me thinks if we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to be Honest, we need not be long in the Search: But some have not been Honest, Few are indeed Honest, and many cannot be Honest in Spite of your Guts; but will look most Demurely in our Faces, while they pick our Pockets: I doe not speak this of those Good Many, that would make us Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest if they could; and pluck up (as they are able) to Land us safely at <hi>Westminster</hi> according to our Bargain; but cannot yet fetch that Shoar, the Winde and Tide are so strong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them: But if Men would be Ingenious in Good Earnest, and have Ears to hear, I know there are many in the World, would say what I think; who are able to speak to better purpose then I: And truely if I had had the smallest En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, my Tale would have been heard; this Book had told no Tales now. Let it be enough then, that this is my minde, If no better Security can be thought of, nor more Happy Expedient for a Settlement, then such a Senate as is proposed, or such <hi>Another House</hi> as that lately Created, and Destroyed; I shall give my Back to these Smiters; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it more happy to sit down under the pleasure of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115293:10"/>the <hi>Grand Signeour;</hi> then to run our selves into <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and Confusion: I am indeed no Enemy, to Honest, Episcopal, and <hi>Puritan</hi> Christians; neither have any Quarrel with <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> or <hi>Independents;</hi> I differ not with their Opinions, so they compell not my Conscience: The <hi>Annabaptist</hi> hurts me not, so his Name signifie his Whole Man; their Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or Uncircumcision availeth me nothing, nor troubles me much, so they will suffer me to be a New Creature, allow me to be a Christian, as well as they: I am not an implacable Enemy to <hi>Caesar,</hi> but can give to <hi>Caesar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caesars;</hi> it having never yet been upon my Spirit, that <hi>Monarchy</hi> is absolutely <hi>Antichristian,</hi> so as one may not live under it, and lead a Peaceable and Quiet Life, <hi>in all Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and Honesty:</hi> However, I am not hardly perswaded, but those whom it may concern, may form some Authority in its stead, every way as well comporting with the Happinesse of this Nation, as that (you see I speak my Mind) I am for Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracy Tooth and Nail: I am not irreconcileable to the Army, but believe we were deeply in their debt, for many good turns; but they have pretty well cut Scores with us of late: and for ought I perceive, if they will pursue this new humble Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Advice (so I call it) for a <hi>Senate,</hi> resolve we shall not dye in their debt. But I am not to be swayed by the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or Interests of any, or all of them; by any means to see Violence Doing, to the undoubted Rights of my Native Country (though it seems to me, I was rather born to be dumb, to matters of <hi>State,</hi> as till now I have been) but I must burst out into this Cry, with the Son of <hi>Craessus, Will you kill my Father?</hi> yea, I wish too many of those severall Opinions, and Interests, were not more wary, then chary of <hi>Englands</hi> Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights. But the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> is my Darling; who I profess before all men, and will maintain it at my perill, are the most happy Constitution, any people in the world can enjoy, if they be not rather Bruits, then Men: and should their little finger, be heavier then the Loyns of a <hi>Senate</hi> (which because Impossibilities may be supposed, I will suppose) ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would I not withdraw my Neck from under that Yoke, but desire to be bored their Servant for ever; wherein should we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115293:10"/>over-shoot our selves in one choyce, we might blame our selves, if we did not mend it in the next: if any think me fool-hardy, and imagine it will not become their wisdome to be so tame; I think they must become such Fools, if they will be wise, and who ever they be, who under the most spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences, shall make voyd so happy a Constitution as <hi>Parliaments,</hi> by whom in realty, we our selves make Laws for our selves; as is most reason we should: those men (be they who they will) shall be <hi>Barbarians</hi> to me, as it is like I am a Heathen, and a Publican to them; and may they as their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness (to say no worse) be put to the <hi>Gibeonitish</hi> shift, that they may succeed them in their Blessing, and be <hi>Hewers of Wood, and Drawers of Water</hi> to <hi>Englands Common-wealth</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>To the Common Soldier I will say nothing; I am no Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineer to the generall Councel of Officers, from whom hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I have expected the great Salvation of the Nation (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me this wrong) though now I am in a fair way to be mistaken: I have this further to say; I have often been sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for your Mis-carriages and Apostasies; yet had great hopes, when he that did let, should be taken out of the way, (whom I thought many were led by, rather out of fear then love) that then some honest hearts, would have appeared ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, for things honest and praise-worthy; and had ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured all my Credit upon it, within this few weeks; but that this wicked World hath made me hardly to believe mens words, till I see them done: however for awhile I keep up some feeble hopes: but since, <hi>your sin revived, and they dyed:</hi> verily I am sorry the Army are the men, they are; could no body else Petition for a <hi>Senate</hi> Co-ordinate in Power with the Parliament: I think most men might, with more safety of Conscience; truly I am affraid of this Spirit of Giddiness: but if yet there be any Vertue, or Honesty remaining with you, think of the Decree that is gone out of your mouths, against us, and our little Ones, to make us cease from being a People, (a free People) from off the Face of <hi>England.</hi> Think with your selves, you that are honest, shall you escape better then the rest? but if you altogether hold your peace, now at this time, then shall enlargement and deliverance come to your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115293:11"/>Brethren some other way, if God see good: but you and your Houses shall be destroyed; and who knows whether you be come unto the Kingdome, for such a time as this. I hope not this Discourse should please all, and yet I doubt it will please some better then I would, out of whose hands (so o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might be supplyed) it should be kept, if I knew their Faces: but some whom it pincheth sadly, I expect should be very angry, who may hap smite me on the Mouth, and ask, <hi>How went this Gift of Prophesie from us to you?</hi> And after what hath been sayd, should I say unto them, <hi>Go, and prosper;</hi> I must needs seem unto them, as one that mocked: and it is a good escape, if they say not of me, <hi>Put this Fellow in hold, and feed him with the bread and Water of Affliction, untill we return in peace:</hi> which when you do, in the way you take, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest part of the Nation have cause to triumph with you; then let me bear the shame of a false Prophet <hi>for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>